<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An information to all good Christians vvithin the kingdome of England, from the noblemen, barrons, borrows, ministers, and commons of the kingdome of Scotland, for vindicating their intentions and actions from the unjust callumnies of their enemies</title>
            <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1639</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 19 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A11656</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21905</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116850</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852065</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852065</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17368</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A11656)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17368)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1362:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An information to all good Christians vvithin the kingdome of England, from the noblemen, barrons, borrows, ministers, and commons of the kingdome of Scotland, for vindicating their intentions and actions from the unjust callumnies of their enemies</title>
                  <author>Church of Scotland. General Assembly.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>13, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iames Bryson,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno Dom. 1639.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>At end: Revised according to the ordinanee [sic] of the generall Assembly .. Edinb. 4 of Feb. 1639.</note>
                  <note>Erroneously attributed to John Dury.</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>One of three variants. This one has the imprint in three lines and "Edinb." at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Scotland --  History --  Charles I, 1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17368:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 85 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:17368:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 85 -->
            <p>
               <hi>AN</hi> INFORMATION to all good Chriſtians vvith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in <hi>the Kingdome of</hi> ENGLAND, from the Noblemen, Barrons, <hi>Borrows, Miniſters, and Commons of the</hi> Kingdome of SCOTLAND, for <hi>vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicating their intentions and actions from the unjuſt callumnies of their enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure/>
            <p>EDINBURGH, Printed by <hi>IAMES BRYSON,</hi> ANNO DOM. 1639.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:17368:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 86 -->
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:17368:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 86 -->
            <head>
               <hi>AN INFORMATION</hi> To all good Chriſtians, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE work of reformation now renewed, and farre advanced in this Kingdome, hath in the whole progreſſe, met with all the oppoſition which the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til malice of Romes emiſſaries our adverſaries could plotte. But God hath hither-to diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed all their intentions, and turned <hi>Achitophels</hi> wiſedome into folly: And now when they cannot beat down the walls of IERUSALEM, they labour to undermine it with calumnies, according to the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable maxime, <hi>&amp; calumniare audacter, ſemper aliquid haerebit,</hi> &amp; like <hi>Tobias, Sanballat,</hi> and ſuch like, will not be wanting to oppoſe mightily the building of <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> by ſaying to the King, <hi>Why is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellious citie builded?</hi> The ſame ſteps are now traced by the authours of novations, in this Church, who taking the advantage of their opportunity (which we want to our great regrate) and being greatly aſſiſted and ſtirred up by ſome of their own coat, pernici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17368:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 87 -->and popiſhly affected, do there-upon preſume to whiſper unto his ſacred Majeſtie, and ſpread a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad in the neighbour Kingdome of <hi>England,</hi> moſt untrue, and damnable aſperſions, (by and attouer the particulars layed to our charge, in the Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, 18 of <hi>December,</hi> which are largely anſwered in our Proteſtation already publiſhed) venting with equall impudence and malice, that we do only pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend religion, but do intend to ſhake off the moſt lawfull yoke of authoritie, by changing the forme of civill government; to invade our neighbour king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of <hi>England,</hi> and inrich our ſelves by the ſpoils thereof. Although our conſcience bear us teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie againſt theſe untruths, and make us think charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, that no men underſtanding rightly Religion and Policie, will grant belief unto theſe aſperſions, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged againſt the bodie of a Church and Kingdome; yet being certainly informed, that the authours of our novations and the arch-enemies of reformation, have laboured to poyſon his Majeſties ſacred Ears with thoſe imputations, and diſperſed the ſame with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen mouth among the ſubjects of <hi>England,</hi> we were forced to vindicat our innocencie and wyp away all impreſſions which thoſe challenges might make in the beliefe of any, firſt by our Supplication given into the Lords of ſecret Councell 31 of <hi>Ianuary,</hi> and now by this our anſwer and publick declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to the world: whereby wee take GOD to wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, that Religion is the only ſubject, conſcience the motive, and reformation the aime of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes: For attaining whereof, wee have never ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from the humble and loyall way of petitioning
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:17368:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 87 -->his Majeſtie for legall redreſſe; but doe yet, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our bound duetie, beg the conſummation of our happie beginnings, by the holding of the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for the ratification of the acts of the Aſſembly indicted by his royall authority; and as we have often hereto-fore profeſſed in our Supplications, religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligiouſly ſworn in our ſolemne Covenant with GOD Almightie, and publickly declared before GOD and men in all our Proteſtations, made in the view of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and earth, that we had never the leaſt intention to caſt off our duetifull obedience unto his Majeſties moſt lawfull authoritie; So we do hereby renew the ſame, and ſolemnely declare, that our loyall breaſts have never harboured any thought againſt our gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soveraigne, his Perſon, and government, to whom wee daily and earneſtly pray the KING of Kings, to grant long and happie reigne over us; and when he ſhall bee crowned with immortality, that there may not want one of his Seed rightly to rule us, and to ſit upon his throne, ſo long as the Sun and Moone indureth. For wee acknowledge that hee is the Lords Vicegerent, ſwaying the Scepter of this Land, tranſmitted to him, by ſucceſſion, of ſo many royall Anceſtours, as none other King in the world can parallell the ſame, and none other Nation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with us in the glorie of Antiquitie, under that lawfull ſubjection, to one Line of native borne Princes: which we will never deface, by any unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall and impious cogitation againſt the Lords A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed; but heartily wiſh that ſhame and confuſion may be printed upon the face of his enemies, and that wee might bee happie in the occaſion to expoſe
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17368:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 88 -->our lives and fortunes to the greateſt hazard, for maintenance of the Perſon and authoritie of our dread Soveraigne, and increaſe of his honour. <hi>Let mercie and truth preſerve the King.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for our intention to invade <hi>England,</hi> we atteſt the everliving GOD, who is conſcious of our moſt ſecret thoughts, that we never had any ſuch deſigne or motion, to offend or wrong in the ſmalleſt mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure any other Nation, much leſſe our neighbour Kingdome, living in one Yle, under one King, with as li<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le controverſie, and as much affection, as hath been betwixt two Nations once at variance, but now happily reconciled, and tyed together by moſt ſtrait bands, which we deſire rather to increaſe then dimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh by any act of unjuſt hoſtility. And albeit we be confident that the inprobabilitie of this challenge, will ſtop the way of all credite to it; yet to confound theſe reporters in their malice, we will ſhortly relate our regrats and fears, our deſires and reſolutions, with that freedome and ſinceritie, which may evidence our brotherly reſpect to the ſubjects of <hi>England,</hi> and controll the falſe ſurmiſes of intentions againſt them: we regrate together with our dear Chriſtian brethren of our neighbour Nation, that we ſhould have ſo evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and ſenſible experiences of the dangerous plots ſet afoot, and intertained by the Church-men of greateſt power in <hi>England,</hi> for introducing novations in Religion, by corrupting the Doctrine, chang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Diſcipline, daily innovating the external<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worſhip of GOD, preaching publickly, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining points of <hi>Arminianiſme,</hi> and heads of pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, defending and advancing preachers and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17368:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 88 -->of that judgement, and allowing books ſtuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fed with that doctrine, fyning, confyning, and ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing all ſuch as in conſcience of their duetie to GOD, labour to oppoſe the doctrine, diſcipline, or worſhip of the Kirk of <hi>Rome,</hi> by their incroaching and uſurping upon the Kings Majeſties prerogative, tyrannizing over the conſcience, goods, and eſtates, of perſons of all qualities within that Kingdome: And not being content to keep within their own pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cinct, did induce, aſſiſt, and incourage the pretended Arch-biſhops, and Biſhops of this Kingdome, to preſſe not only a conformitie of this Church, with that of <hi>England,</hi> in matter of ceremonie, but alſo with the church of <hi>Rome,</hi> in the points moſt ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantially erronious, as appeareth by theſe books of common prayer and canons, found to bee a maſſe of popiſh ſuperſtition, doctrine, and tyrannie, which was confeſſed to have been firſt plotted, then cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected and interlined in <hi>England,</hi> ſent down to their aſſociats the pretended Arch-biſhops, and Biſhoips of this Kingdome, to bee printed and preſſed upon the whole Church here, without order or conſent, as the only forme of divine worſhip and government of the Church, to make us a leading caſe to <hi>England:</hi> required by their letters, Stars-men, Noble-men, and Burghs, to further the advancement thereof, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded his gracious Majeſtie, to declare theſe books, full of popiſh ſuperſtition, yet to bee free of it, and to be fit means of edifying this Church: cauſed his Majeſtie prohibit the lawfull meetings, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſupplications of his Subjects, under pain of trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and to eſteeme of his good Subjects as of trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuors
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17368:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 89 -->and rebels, for diſcovering this wicked plot, complaining thereof, and for their renewing of their nationall Covenant with GOD, and their alledgance to his Majeſtie, to threaten them by publick pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, with utter exterminion, and ruine, hath by their calumnies, moved his Majeſtie to diſcharge under the pain of treaſon, the ſitting of our free ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Aſſembly, indicted by his Majeſtie, after ſo many ſupplications, and to ingadge his royall word of a Prince, to defend all diſobeyers of the Church, to threaten and prepare for an invaſive war againſt his moſt ancient loyall native Kingdome; to diſtruſt all our ſupplications, oathes, and declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, ingenuouſly and humbly made, and thereby they have indevoured ſo farre as in them lyes to alie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate his Majeſties heart from his people, and eſtrange their due bound affections from him, if it were poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible; and in end for the full accompliſhment of their wickednes (as we are informed) have made his Majeſty follow the advice &amp; counſell of profeſſed papiſts, and to intruſt them with the chiefeſt charges of the armes and armies now preparing for the threatned invaſion of this Kingdome, and ſtill intend to raiſe jealouſies in the body of the one Kingdome againſt the other, and ſo to commit them together, which we beſeech GOD to prevent, and hope it ſhall bee above their ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice: The LORD opening the eyes of our Soveraigne, and of our neighbour nation, to diſcover that treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, whereby nothing is intended but to joyn the two Kingdomes in bloudy warre, that ſo reformed Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion may be extinguiſhed and poperie introduced, which then may be eaſily effectuate, when both ſides
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17368:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 89 -->are weakned, and ſo may bee the more eaſily ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed by the papiſts, having all power and charge <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n their hand, being already too ſtrong in <hi>England,</hi> and incouraged with the expectation of forraine helpe, ready to accept that advantage, ſo much prejudiciall to his Majeſties honour, power and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold declarations, for the maintenance of the reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Religion, whereof he is the defender. We have alſo reaſon to regrate, that any within that Kingdome ſhould give more credite to falſe calumnies, cunning<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly invented to foment their jealouſies, and make them prepare for invading us their brethren, then unto our ſolemne Proteſtations, Supplications, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clarations, and Covenant with GOD himſelfe. Yet we are fully confident, that ſuch are only drawen there-unto, partly through the mis-information of our adverſaries, and partly for lack of cleare informa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, concerning our moſt loyall and Chriſtian pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings: And therefore doe moſt heartily wiſh, they may with wiſedome and charity, ſuſpend any further giving credit to things of that kinde, till they may have occaſion to receive full information of the truth And we regrate that any ſhould think the ſtanding of Epiſcopacie in the Church of <hi>Scotland</hi> an juſt ground for invading of, and making war againſt this Nation, and conſequently to raiſe up the old natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall bloud-ſhed and quarrels, which are now hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily changed into a ſweet peaceable conjunction of hearts and affections, ſeeing Epiſcopacie in this Church, is contrare to our ancient reformation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of Faith, and oath of this Church and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, whereby that government was abjured which
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17368:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 90 -->cannot reaſonably offend any other ſtate or Church, who may bee ruled by their own laws and warrand, but as in every matter which falleth in deliberation to be put in execution, Iuſtice ſhould be the mover and efficient, and benefit either in profit or honour uſeth to bee the end; So eſpecially in this weightie buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, it ſhould be well pondered, if this act of inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding us by warre, for keeping our oath to GOD, and obeying the lawfull conſtitutions of our Church and Kingdome, be juſt upon the part of the invader, or if the benefit of re-eſtabliſhng Biſhops upon us will recompenſe the loſſe of ſo much Chriſtian bloud, &amp; hazard of diſſenſion &amp; war, whereof the event depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth upon the LORD of hoſts: but it is obvious to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry mans conſideration, that this war is by our adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries intended for another end, &amp; hath a more deep dangerous reach: other wiſe the Prelates if either good Chriſtians or patriots would rather quit their Minion ambition, and worldly pompe, then ingadge two Kingdomes, with the hazard of true Religion.</p>
            <p>And that none may ſuſpect the ſinceritie of our intentions, the lawfulneſſe of our proceedings, or the truth of our declarations, and accuſations againſt the enemies of our reformation and peace, wee are able, and wiſh to have occaſion to juſtifie the ſame before the world: for unleſſe we ſhould have cloſed our own light, and reſiſted the known will of GOD, acknowledged, ſubſcribed, and ſworne by his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſtie, and our predeceſſours, in a ſolemne Covenant with GOD, and ſo often confirmed and ratified by acts of this church and kingdome, ſince the reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, wee could not omit any thing which we have
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:17368:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 90 -->done. And albeit we be an Church and Kingdome, as free, ancient, and independent, as any other in the world: yet for clearing the minde of our neighbour nation, from all miſ-information, and miſ-conſtruction of our intentions and proceedings, and to verifie the lawfulneſſe, and abſolute neeeſſity of our actions, and acts of the late Aſſembly, we do aſſure our ſelves, that if the Eſtates and Parliament of <hi>England,</hi> were conveened, and the whole pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſe of this buſineſſe faithfully repreſented to them, they would without doubt be ſo farre from cenſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or condemning what we do, that they would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bee moved to become petitioners to his ſacred Majeſtie on our behalfe, and approve of the equitie and loyaltie of all our proceedings in this cauſe: And therefore in the mean time, wee intreat that no true Engliſh heart entertain any jealouſies of us, who are confident of the innocencie of our proceedings and intentions, free hither-to of all blemiſhes againſt our Soveraigne or neighbour nation, as wee do beg the occaſion of manifeſting the ſame to them, and to all the world, as we have upon the knowledge of theſe miſ-reports of us, cleared our ſelves of any ſuch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention by our great oaths every one to another at our moſt frequent meetings.</p>
            <p>The obtaining of this our ſo peaceable and juſt deſire, ſhall not only bee comfortable to us, their Chriſtian brethren, ſerving as a farther tye to unite our affections in time to come, and ſtirre us up to poure our heartie prayers to GDO on their behalfe, but without all queſtion, the righteous Iudge of all the world, ſhall make you reap the fruit thereof one
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17368:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 91 -->day, and who knoweth how ſoone.</p>
            <p>In the mean time our care ſhall bee upon all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions to make it appear clearly to all the world, how farre it hath alwayes been (and by the grace of GOD ever ſhall bee) from our intention firſt or laſt, to offer the leaſt act of hoſtilitie to our neighbour Kingdome, except in ſo farre as we ſhall bee nece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitat in our own defence: and though (as GOD for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid) we ſhould be forced thereunto, yet ſhall we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine unwilling to conceive things of that kinde, to flow from the body of that Kingdome, with whom we intend no nationall quarrell, neither minde to wrangle with them, except in the caſe of invaſion from them, but rather that this ſturre hath been con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trived and ſet forward by ſome ill affected perſons to both kingdomes, with whom only our queſtion is, &amp; to whom alone we may juſtly intend according to their deſert, as men who are ſet to ingadge both king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes in ſo bloudie a warre for their own baſe ends: and although a party raiſed from among our ſelves, fomented, and maintained from abroad, from whence we finde the ſinews of that body within our ſelves to bee derived and maintained, may juſtly ſeeme to ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate, yet the vanitie and weakneſſe of our inteſtine adverſaries, even in this caſe of offence, is ſo farre from making us take fire, without manifeſt hoſtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie offered, or ingadging us in any violent courſe that may interrupt the brotherly love and concord of theſe two Kingdoms, or blemiſh our holy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion in the leaſt degree, as we are confident, no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious miſ-reports of our common adverſaries, will induce our deare brethren to quarrell with us, for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17368:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 91 -->ſeeking to enjoy our Religion in puritie and our laws and liberties, according to the fundamentall conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of our Church and ſtate, when we are ſo well affected to them, as we are truely ſenſible of their grievous burthens, &amp; intolerable ſufferings from the tyrannie of their hierarchie, and the fearfull bondage they underlye from the wicked counſel of their Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, ſuggeſted from Rome, and producing ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous innovations both in Religion and Policie.</p>
            <p>This ſincere manifeſtation of our reall intentions, wee finde our ſelves obliged, to publiſh for ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying all good Subjects in our neighbour nation, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing confident they are as deſirous to be confirmed in their good opinion of us, and ſo to be armed againſt all ſlanders and calumnies of thoſe that indevour the finall overthrow and utter exterminion of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Chriſt Ieſus from this whole Iſland: wherof we pray God, to avert the danger, &amp; to grant us peace and puritie, which is the height of our deſire: for procuring whereof we ſhall employ none other wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons (except we be enforced) but faſting and prayer to GOD Almightie and humble ſupplications to our gracious Soveraigne.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Reviſed according to the ordinance of the generall Aſſembly, by me <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. A. Ihonſtoun</hi> Clerk thereto:</signed>
               <dateline>Edinb. <date>4 of Feb. 1639.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
